Hi everyone.
This is the presentation for
the paper of Thirty-two Years of IEEE VIS:
Authors, Fields of Study and Citations.
VIS recently positioned itself
within the field
of data science.
However, this does not tell us
where VIS is in
science overall.
For example, we don't
know which fields
VIS is citing and which
fields are citing VIS.
The official website of
IEEE VIS mentioned
that: The conference will
convene an international
community of
researchers and practitioners
from universities,
government, and industry to
exchange recent findings.
However, we don't know
how many authors are from
universities, government,
and industry.
That is, we don't know
the statistics of
author affiliations
in the past 32 years.
Here, we try to answer
these two questions.
First, where VIS stands in science?
And second, where VIS authors
are from and how
they collaborated.
To answer these two questions,
we collected all the
relevant paper DOIs
in the past 32 years
from 1990 to 2021.
Based on those DOIs, we
collected data on paper,
authors and fields of study
from OpenAlex and IEEEXplore
More details
about the procedure can
be found in this diagram.
And we published our dataset
in the official website
of our project.
Here we'll report the results.
In terms of the general trends.
We found that VIS has
been increasingly popular,
which is evident
in the increasing number of
publications each year and
the increasing number of
unique authors each year.
VIS is also becoming
more impactful because
an increasing number of
citations are from
non-VIS papers.
We found that there were
more and more collaborations
in VIS because
the proportion of
cross-country and
cross-type collaborations
has been increasing.
By "cross-type", we mean
the collaboration between
authors from universities
are non-educational
affiliations.
Those collaborations,
however, were
concentrated because,
for example,
the graph here shows that
the top ten countries were
present in 98% of
all the cross-country
collaborations
in the past 32 years.
In terms of the geographical
aspect of authors,
we've found that an
increasing number
of countries are
participating in VIS.
For example, in 2021,
authors from 26 countries
participated in VIS,
whereas only five countries
participating in the first
VIS conference in 1990.
This participatino is
concentrated in terms of
author country origins and also
in terms of the continent.
There are some redistributions
in the participation.
For example, the percentage of
authors from the
United States has been
constantly declining
and the percentage
of authors from China
has been increasing.
In terms of author
affiliation types.
We've found that authors from
universities dominated VIS.
Earlier.
We showed that cross-type collaborations
have been increasing.
However, here we've found that the
proportion of authors from
non-educational affiliations
has been constantly declining.
The right panel shows
that although there is
an increasing number of
authors from educational
affiliations,
the number of authors from
non-educational affiliations,
has been stabilizing at around
a 100 the past 32 years.
So combining these two results,
we can know that
the small but stable number
of authors from non-educational
affiliations have been actively
participating in VIS
projects in the past 32 years.
In terms of fields of study,
this graph shows
the distribution of
the lowest level concepts or
fields of study in VIS papers.
And we've found that most
of the papers were about
computer science
and mathematics.
The same is for papers that
are referenced in VIS.
And papers that are citing VIS.
And that's why we say
that VIS is mainly
about, built upon, and
impacting computer
science and mathematics.
We also found a concentration
of concepts in these papers.
Because at each level,
only a few concepts were
frequently appearing
in VIS papers.
We also examined the citation
flows based on fields of study.
The left panel shows
the citation flows
from papers that are
referenced in VIS to VIS.
And the right panel shows
the citations flows
from VIS papers,
to papers that
are citing VIS.
And these two figures showed
that citations mostly flow
between the same
set of concepts.
The interactive
visualizations can be
found in the official
website of our project.
In terms of citations,
we found that the
lion's share of
citations were taken
by the top papers.
For example,
the top 20% papers,
took 60% of all the citations.
We ran a regression analysis to
see what factors are influencing
the number of citations.
And we found that earlier
works, journal papers,
and papers that have won
an award have significantly
more citations.
To recap, we've found
that VIS has been
becoming increasingly popular,
impactful and collaborative.
We've found that geographically,
authors are diverse but
concentrated. In terms of
author affiliation
types, we found
that authors from
universities dominated VIS.
In terms of fields of study,
we found that VIS is
mainly about, built upon
and impacting computer
science and mathematics.
And we also found about
citations flow mostly between
the same set of concepts.
Our regression analysis
shows that earlier works,
journal papers and award
winning papers had
more citations.
Thank you, and I'm happy
to take questions.